Guide to the John Ross papers SC1320
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Ross papers
1950-2012
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baysinger, Grace
SC1320
9.25 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Content Description
Ross' biographical information and student theses as well as administrative, subject, and travel files.
Biographical / Historical
John Ross earned a BS in Chemistry at Queens College in 1948, and a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1951. Ross was the Camille and Henry Dreyfus Professor of Chemistry at Stanford University, from 1983 to 1989. He began his faculty career as an assistant professor in chemistry at Brown University in 1953. In 1966, Ross joined the chemistry department faculty at MIT, where he served as chair from 1966 to 1971. He came to Stanford University in 1980 as a professor of chemistry and was department chair from 1983 to 1989. Ross was elected to the National Academy of Sciences and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences; he received the U.S. National Medal of Science in 2000 from President Clinton. John Ross died in February 2017.
Excerpted from:
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Chemistry -- Study and teaching.; Chemical kinetics.; Statistical mechanics.; Baysinger, Grace; Stanford University. Department of Chemistry. Faculty
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2017-174
  - Piper, Lawrence Gibson,”Dissociation of alkali halides in collisions with high energy argon.”, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Makowski, Jennifer Ann, “A molecular beam study of methyl radical reactions with halogens: product angular and velocity distributions.”, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bimpong-Bota, Kofi, “Chemical instability effects due to localized reactions., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thompson Milton Sloane, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wang, Tieh-Chu, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hammond, Robert Hume, “A study of ionizing collisions of argon atoms with argon atoms and of helium atoms with helium atoms.”, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hudson, Mary Suzanne Speck, “Studies in the theory of chemical reaction kinetics.”, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - McFadden, David Lee, “Molecular beam study of polyatomic free radical reactions.”, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gracki, John Alexander, “The viscosity of compressed nitrogen, helium, hydrogen, and argon from -100 to 25 C.”, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Freund, Albrecht, “Unterscheidung von deterministischem Chaos und verstärkten Fluktuationen in einem experimentellen System: die Belousov-Zhabotinskii Reaktion im CSTR.”, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Metiu, Horia Ion, “Symmetry in chemical reactions.”, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Creel, Clifford L., “Hysteresis and Multiple Stationary States in a Chemical Reaction.”, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Huntington, John Hermann, “Direct interaction theory of reactive molecular collisions. Alkali metals plus halides.”, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Moursund, Anne Loreen, “The elastic and reactive scattering of K by HC₁, CH₃Br, and HI in crossed molecular beams.”, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eu, Byung Chan, “R-matrix theory for elastic and reactive molecular scattering.”, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Man-hap Lau, “The non-reactive scattering of Cs by HBr and neopentane., 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Calvit Herndon Williams, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Burton, Randolph H., “Molecular beam study of the chemi-ionization reaction of barium with chlorine.”, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bodet, Jean-Marie, “Étude expérimentale de phénomènes d'auto-organisation spatiale dans les systèmes chimiques hors d'équilibre.”, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Richetti, Philippe, “Etudes théoriques et numériques des dynamiques chaotiques de la réaction de Belousov-Zhabotinskii.”, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Creel, Clifford L., “Hysteresis and Multiple Stationary States in a Chemical Reaction.”, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ross, John, “221st American Chemical Society National Meeting”, 2001 Apr (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ross, John, “Self-Diffusion of Gases.”, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Picher, Elgar, “Self-Organization in Biological and Chemical Model Systems, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Richard William Roberts, 1959 Jul (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Villa, Carlos Luis, “Studies in Chemical Dynamics: Information Theory and the Franck-Condon Model”, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lee, Myung Woo, “The Elastic Scattering of K and Cs for Reactive and Nonreactive Systems in Crossed Molecular Beams.”, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Flynn, George Patrick, “The viscosity of nitrogen and argon as a function of density and temperature.”, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lemaire, Normand Arthur, “The viscosity of helium and neon as a function of density and temperature.”, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Choi, Sang Il, “Quantum corrections for transport coefficients.”, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pyun, Chong Wha, “Non-equilibrium molecular distributions and the rates of chemical reactions.”, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hanks, Russell Vandervort, “An experimental study of the viscosities of compressed gases.”, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ross, John, “Biographical sketches and reminiscences of the graduate students, post doctoral associates, collaborators, and colleagues of John Ross: published in conjunction with a symposium in honor of John Ross' 70th birthday: Chemical kinetics: from molecular beams to biological instabilities: Apr 12, 1997, Stanford University.”, 1997 Apr 12 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2017-194
  - Accomodation Folder (for visiting Profs. students), 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Astumian, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 184, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AAAS, 2002-2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1958-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B, 2002-2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Beckman Proposal (Ron Davis submitted), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Permissions, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - C, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapters (floppy disks), 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Award, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dahl, Klaus, 1984-1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Georgetown, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - D, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - E, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nomination for National Medal of Technology Stan Ovshinsky, 1998 Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Nomination for National Inventors Hall of Fame Stan Ovshinsky, 1998 Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memorandum I and Memorandum II, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Energy Conversion Devices, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Equipment (JR lab equipment) dissolution, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - F, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - G, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Harvey nomination, 2001 Sep (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - H, 1998-2009 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - I (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - J, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - K, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - L, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Marcel, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - M, 1999-2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - MIT (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Harden McConnell, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - O, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - T. Oefner, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Orwar, Owe (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Genetics (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - OM Ombudsman, 2004-2011 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - For Manuscript Submittal: Manuscripts contributed by members (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence: Proceedings of the National Academy, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Proceedings of the National Academy, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - P, 1998-2008 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Q, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - R, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Yu - Fen Hung, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Student Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - S, 2003-2009 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Turing - Liesegang, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - T, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - U (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - V (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - W (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Weizmann (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - XYZ (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Calendars (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - NSF, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - John Ross nomination, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Misc introduction (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - News, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - For Manuscript submittal: manuscript checklist/ request for opinion forms, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Agios, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Random Memory Depth, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Federico, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Julio Banga, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Alex Carlos random depth, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New Work (R. Levine) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Drawer contents (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Diagram (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Congratulations: Irving Langmuir Award in Chemical Physics, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - International Board Executive Board Committees (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Academic Activities John Ross, 1964-2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Planners, 2009-2012 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - MSS submittal, 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Himself, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - John Ross photographs (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Biographical Material - Jr, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chairman negotiations (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - John Ross - Personal File (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Montana (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - New York Times write up: John Ross, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dr. John Ross, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Biography: Dr. John Ross (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Informatica Article (Spain) John Ross (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Spain Trip File, 1992 May (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Beckman Conf, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - President of Stanford, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Prof. Ross USC, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - ACS Orlando, IA, 2002 Aug 7-11 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Boston (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Austria, 2002 Apr - May (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Santa Cruz, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Iowa St., 2002 Oct (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - CA Separation Soc. SF, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - GRC California, 2001 Mar 11 - 16 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Berkeley, 2001 Jan 24 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - ICAM Workshop Santa Fe, 2001 Jan 7-12 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Chicago CDOEI, 2001 May 21-22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - ACS Meeting San Diego, 2001 Apr (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Virginia Toronto Washington, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - W2MN, 2005 Jan (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Nov Trip: Israel, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Travel old itineraries, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Conference on Spatial Inhomogeneities Transient. Behavior, 1987 Aug - Sep (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - College de France, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Conference College de France Paris - Israel, 1988 Autumn (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Australia, 1975 Aug (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Gordon Research Conference, 2000 Aug (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - CRM Universite de Montreal, Montreal, 2000 Sep 9-13 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Third Flory Conference, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Centenniel meeting APS Atlanta, 1999 Mar (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Stanford Admit Weekend, 1999 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Santa Barbara Trip Horia Metiu, 1999 May 2-4 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Design principles for the immune… meeting - Santa Fe, 1999 Jul 11-16 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Boston - NY, 1999 Oct (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Symposium on non-linear dynamics in Chemistry, Hawaii, 2000 Dec 14-19 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Nonlinear dynamics in Biology Chemistry, 1999 Sep 3-4 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Rothman Physics, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ross Wiley Systems biol., 2009 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Review - Elmau Berichte… (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Heidelberg, 2011 May (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - U of Chicago, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Harvard, NH, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lecture - Chem Kinetics, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - UCSD, 2008 Oct 17 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Stanford, 2008 Sep 25 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Crete, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - DARDA, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - China, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - La Jolla, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - ILL, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - E., 2006 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Patent 4, 118, 296, 5, 580, 623, 1978-1996 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Journal of Physical Chemistry, 1996 Dec 5 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Biographical Sketches and Reminiscences of the Graduate Students, Post Doctoral Associates, Collaborators, and Colleagues of John Ross, 1997 Apr 12 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Garfinkle, M., 1996 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - G, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - R.I., 1989-1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Show after, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - paper, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Research Proposals, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Epidemiology, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Presented to B.N., 2005 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Genomics (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Adventures in Vaccuums, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Freshman seminar (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Freshman Seminar - JR will teach, 1998 Spring (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - On Understanding Science (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chem 31, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 31, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chemistry notes (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chem 171, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - M. Gage, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Misc. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Alex, Villaverde (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Endowed Professorships at MIT (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - photograph (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - photograph (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Coronation of King John, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Attendee List (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - DOE meeting - Argonne Ill, 1998 May 13-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Seminar - UCSF Dept. Pharmaceutical Chemistry, 1998 May 29 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Colloquium - S.F. State, 1998 Oct 26 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dynamics of Biological Processes, Symposium with Manfred Eigen, 1998 Aug - Sep (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - La Jolla trip file, 1998 Feb 15-19 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - A Workshop for the IAP: Discussion, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NASA Ames Research Center Colloquium, 1998 Mar 31 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Stanford Admit Weekend Academic Expo, 1998 Apr 23-25 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Freshman Seminar - Spring Quarter, 1998 Apr - Jun (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Gordon Conference, 1997 Jul 13-18 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Conference which Adam will attend - ICOBIP, 1997 Mar 2-4 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Workshop, France (Adam, or John, or both will attend), 1997 Mar 16-22 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Hopkins Marine Station, 1997 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - James Franck Institute Colloquium, 1997 May 27 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Europe Trip - Budapest/Vienna, 1997 Sep (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Workshop (Michigan- Dykman), 1997 Aug 17-21 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Conference which Adam will Attend - Aspen workshop, 1997 Aug (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Biophysical Chemistry symposium Las Vegas, 1997 Sep 7-11 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Sci. Acad. Board Meeting Weizmann Institute, 1997 Nov (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Transmission, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - NATO Workshop - Hanover, Germany JR will not attend - Adam, 1996 May (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Europe Trip, 1996 Sep (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - AFOSR Meeting - Boulder, Colorado, 1996 Jun 2-5 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 4th IUPAC Conference Osaka, Japan, 1996 Aug 25-30 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Manfred Eigen/La Jolla Trip, 1997 Nov 14-16 (Box 4, Folder 30)